IAN LOVEALL: Hi.
We're talking about mural painting today; light and shadow.
Light and shadow are the keys to realistic painting.
If you look at this example here, we've got a lot of cast shadow going on.
Normally, mural painters will sort of shy away from cast shadow because it's dark and we usually want to avoid dark in a painting on a wall because it closes in the space.
I'm telling you, do not be afraid of shadows.
This is what's going to make your painting pop.
So, for example, we have a lot of cast shadows here.
We have a shadow being cast from the bouquet, the urn, we have a cast shadow here from the dove, and a lot of shadow going on under the architectural work here.
Our light source is that window over there, and so as the light comes streaming in, it's going to be blocked by any object in its path.
For example, this border here is going to block the light and the wall directly behind is not going to receive any light, creating a cast shadow.
Again, down here along the bottom edge, cast shadow.
Even the vines that are growing up along the wall will create cast shadows against the wall where the vine is blocking the light, falling on the wall surface.